Guide to the John Stevenson Papers, 1943-1983 RL.01252
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Stevenson papers
1943-1983 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stevenson, John Alun
RL.01252
18 Linear Feet
Pioneer in direct mail, director of Greystone Press which specialized in subscription encyclopedias and continuity series books. The John Stevenson papers span the years 1947-1983 and include correspondence, advertising designs, direct mail/direct marketing mailings, financial records and other materials that document Stevenson's career with Greystone Press selling encyclopedias, book club subscriptions, literary continuity series and home reference manuals. Some of the materials were co-produced by Fred Breismeister, a former New York Post copywriter. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
7,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Stevenson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Biographical Note
Born in England; attended London School of Economics; early career as journalist (20th Century Fox, New York Post); founded Book Presentations 1942 and Fiction Book Club 1946. Acquired Greystone Press 1943 which he ran until retiring in the early 1990s. Died Feb. 16, 2002, New York, N.Y.
Collection Overview
The John Stevenson papers span the years 1947-1983 and include correspondence, advertising designs, direct mail/direct marketing mailings, financial records and other materials that document Stevenson's career with Greystone Press selling encyclopedias, book club subscriptions, literary continuity series and home reference manuals. Some of the materials were co-produced by Fred Breismeister, a former New York Post copywriter.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files, Account Files, Direct Marketing Examples, and Financial Records.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Arlie Slabaugh Collection of Direct Mail Literature
J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter Papers
Lester Wunderman Papers
National Press Company Advertising and Promotional Materials Collection
Wunderman Archives
Advertising, Direct-mail -- United States -- History; Advertising, Direct-mail -- History; Advertising, Direct-mail; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- History; Advertising; Advertising, Direct marketing -- History; Advertising, Direct marketing -- United States -- History; Book clubs (Booksellers); Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Encyclopedias and dictionaries -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Booksellers and bookselling -- Colportage, subscription trade, etc.; Booksellers and bookselling; Encyclopedias and dictionaries -- Marketing; Advertising, Direct marketing; Greystone Publishing Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Stevenson, John (John Alun), d. 2002; Stevenson, John Alun
- General Files Series, 1947-1983 and undated
  - Canadian operations, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Commissions paid by Greystone to John Stevenson, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - Contests/Fiction Book Club, 1947-1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Contract file, lists of titles, undated (Box 1)
  - Eastern Air Conditioning, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - F&E Sales/Check Writer, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - Sutson Ltd., finance and miscellaneous, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
- Account Files Series
  - 100 Great Lives, 1944 (Box 1)
  - 101 of the World's Greatest Books, 1950-1966 (Box 1)
  - 201 Valuable Free Plans for the Handyman, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - 501 Valuable Free Things, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - 501 Ways to Save on Doctor, Dentist and Drug Bills, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - A Man's Reader, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Allenite Tool Co., 1973 (Box 1)
  - American Everyday Cookbook, 1946 (Box 1)
  - American Sexual Behavior and the Kinsey Report, 1952-1977 (Box 1)
  - America's Gardens, 1966-1976 (Box 1)
  - Animal Kingdom, 1953-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Art of the World, 1965-1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Associated Book Clubs (South Africa), 1967-1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Back to Mandalay, 1951-1956 (Box 2)
  - Barnstable Corp., 1974 (Box 2)
  - Bartlett's Familiar Quotations, 1955-1959 (Box 2)
  - Battles and Leaders of the Civil War, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Better English Made Easy, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
  - Better Reading Program, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Bible in Pictures, 1953-1957, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bible in Pictures (French edition), 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Bible in Pictures (Spanish edition), 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Bobley Publishing, 1966-1975 (Box 2)
  - Book Club Guild, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Book of the Month Club, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Books & Periodicals, Inc., 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Bottom's Up, 1952-1966 (Box 3)
  - Cadillac Publishing, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Cambridge Book Co., 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Children's Hour, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - College Marketing & Research Corp./Man and Woman: The Encyclopedia of Adult Relationships, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Dolls, 1948-1964 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Electrical Repairs, 1952-1954 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Embroidery, 1948-1955 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Home Repairs, 1949-1960 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Interior Decorating, 1948-1955 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Mothercraft, 1950-1962 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Sewing, 1943-1972 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Table Setting, 1953-1965 (Box 3)
  - Complete Book of Wildflowers, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Consolidated Book Publishers, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - Coronet Magazine, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Culbertson's Card Games Complete, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
  - Curtis Publishing, 1964-1966 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Publishing/Encyclopedia of Gardening, 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Publishing/Sutson Ltd., 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Publishing/The World and Its People, 1963-1969 (Box 4)
  - Desmond J. Meehan Associates, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Dictionary of Interior Design, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
  - Discovering Antiques, 1972-1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Doctor Looks at Life, 1952-1958 (Box 4)
  - Dog Care, 1953-1976 (Box 4)
  - Douglas Dunhill/Gulf Oil, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Early American Society, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Encyclopedia of Art, 1962-1979 (Box 4)
  - Encyclopedia of Decorating, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
  - Encyclopedia of Good Decorating and Home Improvement, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia of Guns, Hunting and Fishing, 1949-1963 (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia of Photography, 1962-1980, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Eugene Schuster, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Every Woman's Standard Guide to Home and Child Care, 1951-1965 (Box 5)
  - Executive Book Club, 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Exploring Nature with Your Child, 1951-1976 (Box 5)
  - Fairbanks Associates, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Family Health Guide, 1958-1963 (Box 5)
  - Family Legal Advisor, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Family Physician, 1949-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Family Physician A to Z, 1965-1974 (Box 5)
  - Family Physician/Family Health Guide, 1958-1965 (Box 6)
  - Fawcett Publications, 1971-1975 (Box 6)
  - First Books/Franklin Watts, 1955-1957 (Box 6)
  - First Books/Peek, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - Foundations of Science, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Frank C. Henry, contracts and commissions, 1956-1962 (Box 6)
  - Fulton Sheen Sunday Missal, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Gache Publishing, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Gardens Around the World, 1966-1975 (Box 6)
  - Gardening Encyclopedia, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Gertrude Lawrence as Mrs. A., 1954-1966 (Box 6)
  - Golden Hands, 1975-1978 (Box 6)
  - Golden Hands Enclopedia of Crafts, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Good Housekeeping, 1959-1963 (Box 6)
  - Goren's Hoyle, 1961-1966 (Box 6)
  - Great Masters, 1971-1977 (Box 6)
  - Greystone Classics, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Greystone/Doubleday, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Guiding Light Bible, 1956-1973 (Box 6)
  - Guild Press, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Handicrafts and Hobbies, 1948, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Harding Foundation, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
  - Hat Book, undated (Box 6)
  - Hawthorn Books, 1956-1973 (Box 7)
  - Hearst Corporation, 1960-1978, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Heirloom Bible/Catholic Bible, 1959-1964 (Box 7)
  - History of the Second World War, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Horticultural Society, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Houghton-Mifflin/North Star Book Club, 1963 (Box 7)
  - How I Pick Winners, 1953 (Box 7)
  - How to Build and Remodel Your Home, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
  - How to Build Your Own Furniture, 1951 (Box 7)
  - How to Get Better Medical Care for Less Money, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
  - How to Help Your Husband Get Ahead, 1953-1976 (Box 7)
  - How to Increase Your Mental and Physical Efficiency, 1954 (Box 7)
  - How to Make Money with Your Art, 1950 (Box 7)
  - How to Make the Most of Every Day/New Way to Relax, 1949-1969, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Illustrated Encyclopedia of Animal Life, 1964-1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Illustrated Library of the World and Its People, 1964-1966 (Box 8)
  - International Computer Sciences, 1971 (Box 8)
  - It's a Sin to Be Fat, 1948-1956 (Box 8)
  - It's Fun to Eat and Lose Weight, 1947 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Flower Arrangements, 1968-1975 (Box 8)
  - Joy of Sex, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Les Editions Denoël, 1953-1955 (Box 8)
  - Library of Science and Invention, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Lincoln Press, 1976 (Box 8)
  - Living Language Courses, 1958, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Living Shakespeare, 1962 (Box 8)
  - London Arts, Inc., 1972-1973 (Box 8)
  - Lunch Box, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Made Simple, 1956-1960 (Box 8)
  - Magic of Believing, 1952 (Box 8)
  - Man & Woman, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
  - Marboro Books, 1958-1959 (Box 8)
  - Mark Twain, 1967-1972 (Box 8)
  - Marriage Counselor, 1952-1957 (Box 8)
  - Martin & Murray, 1957 (Box 8)
  - Mattel Encyclopedia of Decorating, 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - McCall's Encylopedia of Good Decorating and Home Improvement, 1970 (Box 9)
  - McCall's New Complete Book of Sewing and Dressmaking, 1950-1962 (Box 9)
  - McKibbon & Son, 1957-1962 (Box 9)
  - Medical Encyclopedia, 1960-1962 (Box 9)
  - Médecine A á Z (French), 1971-1974 (Box 9)
  - Memorial Bibles, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Meredith/Garden Encyclopedia, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Modern Handcraft/Mid-America, 1967-1974 (Box 9)
  - Museum Lane Publishing, 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - Mythology, 1972-1976 (Box 9)
  - Nature Lover's Treasury, 1946-1947 (Box 9)
  - New Caxton Encyclopedia, 1973 (Box 9)
  - New Edition Calorie Counter, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - New Illustrated Encyclopedia of Gardening, 1952-1967 (Box 9)
  - New International Illustrated Encyclopedia of Art, 1962-1972 (Box 9)
  - New Medical Encyclopedia, 1961 (Box 9)
  - New Popular History of the World, 1950-1974 (Box 9)
  - Nobel Prize Library, 1971-1979 (Box 9)
  - Our of this World, 1950-1966 (Box 10)
  - P.F. Collier & Sons, 1949-1954 (Box 10)
  - Paint It Yourself, 1954-1963 (Box 10)
  - Personal Affairs Manual, 1954-1966 (Box 10)
  - Practical Encyclopedia of Decorating, 1969-1977 (Box 10)
  - Practical English, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - Practical Handyman Encyclopedia, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Practical Handyman's Guide, 1965-1967 (Box 10)
  - Practical Home Handyman, 1953 (Box 10)
  - Prudential Insurance, 1954-1973 (Box 10)
  - Pyrex Prize Recipes, 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - R.A. Associates, 1963-1968 (Box 10)
  - Replogle Globes, 1957 (Box 10)
  - Road is Yours, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Roses and Home Flower Arranging, 1951-1958 (Box 10)
  - Sewing, 1972-1976 (Box 10)
  - Sewing Book (Sears), 1975 (Box 10)
  - Sexual Feeling in Married Men and Women, 1952-1966 (Box 10)
  - Shrines of the World, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - Simon & Schuster, 1954-1955 (Box 10)
  - Simon & Schuster/Complete Medical Guide, 1956 (Box 10)
  - Sloan-Ashland, 1956 (Box 10)
  - Small Baby Book, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Society of Illustrators Christmas Cards, 1955 (Box 10)
  - Special Diet Cook Book, 1952-1968 (Box 11)
  - Standard Book of American Antique Furniture, 1950 (Box 11)
  - Standard Book of Fishing, 1955-1965 (Box 11)
  - Standard Book of Home Repair, 1955 (Box 11)
  - Standard Book of Quilt Making and Collecting, 1949-1978 (Box 11)
  - Standard Reference Works Publishing Co., 1962-1967 (Box 11)
  - Story of Jesus, 1954-1958 (Box 11)
  - Sutson/De Fil en Aiguille (French), 1976 (Box 11)
  - Technical Industry Expositions, Inc., 1968 (Box 11)
  - Through Golden Windows, 1958-1962 (Box 11)
  - To the Bride, 1955-1963 (Box 11)
  - True Magazine Man-to-Man Club, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Universal Educational Guild, 1954-1959 (Box 11)
  - USA Nationwide Discount Booklet, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Walgreen Drug Stores, Inc., 1960 (Box 11)
  - Webster's Dictionary, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Wildflowers of America, 1962-1976 (Box 11)
  - Woman's Home Companion Garden Book, 1954-1961 (Box 11)
  - World and Its People, 1962-1980, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - World Scope Publishers, 1960-1963 (Box 12)
  - World's Great Thinkers, 1957-1966 (Box 12)
  - World's Greatest Literature, 1961-1962 (Box 12)
  - You and Your Hand, 1948 (Box 12)
  - You and Your Job, 1958-1969 (Box 12)
  - You Can Relax, 1959 (Box 12)
- Direct Mail Examples
  - 101 of the World's Greatest Books (Box 12)
  - 201 Free Plans for You (Box 12)
  - 501 Valuable Free Tips and Things (Box 12)
  - 501 Ways to Save on Doctor, Hospital. Dental and Drug Bills (Box 12)
  - Alpha Encyclopedia (Box 12)
  - Art from Found Objects (Box 12)
  - Art of the World (Box 12)
  - At a Glance Recipes (Box 12)
  - Bible in Pictures (Box 12)
  - Complete Book of Sewing (Box 12)
  - Complete Charlie Brown Library (Box 12)
  - Cosmopolitan Book Club (Box 12)
  - Cosmopolitan Love Book (Box 12)
  - Creative Hands (Box 12)
  - Discovering Antiques (Box 12)
  - Dollarwise--Family Money Management Service (Box 12)
  - Encyclopedia of 1001 Valuable Free Things (Box 12)
  - Encyclopedia of Gardening, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Encyclopedia of Modern Health (Box 13)
  - Encyclopedia of Photography, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Encyclopedia of U.S. Government Benefits (Box 14)
  - Enemies of the People (Box 14)
  - Exploring Nature with Your Child (Box 14)
  - Family Encyclopedia of Essential Knowledge (Box 14)
  - Family Legal Advisor (Box 14)
  - Family Physician A to Z (Box 14)
  - First Ladies' Cook Book (Box 14)
  - Foundations of Science (Box 14)
  - Golden Hands (Box 14)
  - Golden Treasury of Cooking (Box 14)
  - Grandes Énigmes de l'Univers (French) (Box 14)
  - Home and Family Medical Emergencies (Box 14)
  - Illustrated Encyclopedia of Animal Life (Box 14)
  - Illustrated Encyclopedia of the Animal Kingdom (Box 14)
  - International Graphic Arts Auction Catalog, 1971 (Box 14)
  - International Illustrated Encyclopedia of Art (Box 14)
  - La Bible en Images (French) (Box 14)
  - La Faune (French) (Box 14)
  - Living Shakespeare (Box 14)
  - Man & Woman (Box 14)
  - Man to Man Book Club (Box 15)
  - New Illustrated Encyclopedia of Gardening, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - New Worlds Family Globe Set (Box 15)
  - Nobel Prize Library (Box 15)
  - Practical Encyclopedia of Good Decorating and Home Improvement, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Practical Handyman's Encyclopedia (Box 15)
  - Presidents of the United States (Box 15)
  - Table Setting and Flower Arrangement (Box 15)
  - Works of Mark Twain (Box 15)
  - World and Its People (Box 15)
  - World Library of Mythology (Box 15)
- Large Format Materials Series
  - General Files
    - Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 16)
    - Finance--Capitol Record Club, 1962 (Box 16)
  - Advertising Designs
    - Book images, undated (Box 16)
    - Booklist, 1969 (Box 16)
    - Complete Book of Sewing, undated (Box 16)
    - Direct marketing mailers (Box 16)
    - Encyclopedia of Gardening (Box 16)
    - Encyclopedia of Modern Health (Box 16)
    - Good Decorating and Home Improvement (Box 16)
    - Handyman circulars (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Creative Binder
    - 501 Valuable Things, 1972 (Box 17)
    - Art of the World, undated (Box 17)
    - Catholic Digest Book Club, 1959-1963 (Box 17)
    - Children's Hour Library, undated (Box 17)
    - Cosmopolitan Book Club, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Creative Hands, 1976 (Box 17)
    - Discovering Antiques (Canada), 1973 (Box 17)
    - Encyclopédie Complète de la Couture/Médecine A á Z (French, Canada), undated (Box 17)
    - Encyclopedia of Animal Life, 1961-1966 (Box 17)
    - Encyclopedia of Art, 1971 (Box 17)
    - Encyclopedia of Gardening, 1963-1974 (Box 17)
    - Encyclopedia of Photography, 1964-1974, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Family Physician A to Z, undated (Box 17)
    - Golfer's Book Club, undated (Box 17)
    - Living Literature/Living Languages, 1961 (Box 17)
    - Living Shakespeare, undated (Box 17)
    - Man & Woman, 1973-1976 (Box 17)
    - Multiple campaigns, undated (Box 17)
    - Newsprint miscellaneous, 1966-1973 (Box 17)
    - Practical Encyclopedia of Good Decorating and Home Improvement, 1971-1974 (Box 17)
    - Practical Handyman's Encyclopedia, 1963-1976, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - World & Its People, 1965-1967 (Box 17)
  - Financial Papers
    - General Ledger, 1980 Jan.-1981 Mar., 14 folders (Box 17)
    - General Ledger, 1981 Apr.-Dec., 9 folders (Box 18)
    - Creative Hands sales, 1979 Sept.-1981 Feb. (Box 18)
    - Gardening encyclopedia sales, 1979 Sept.-1981 Feb. (Box 18)
    - Greystone Press sales, 1979 Sept.-1981 Jan. (Box 18)
    - Handyman encyclopedia sales, 1979 Sept.-1981 June (Box 18)
    - Juston/Sutson Ltd., combined stock and transfer ledger, 1954-1956 (Box 18)
    - Juston/Sutson Ltd., stock book, 1954 (Box 18)
    - Ledgers, 1972-1974 (Box 19)
    - Ledgers, 1974-1976 (Box 20)
    - Ledgers, 1976-1977 (Box 21)
    - Ledgers, 1977-1979 (Box 22)
    - Sutson of Delaware, Inc., minute book and stock ledger, 1982 (Box 23)
  - Advertising Designs
    - 101 of the World's Greatest Books (Box 24)
    - Bible in Pictures (Box 24)
    - Complete Book of Sewing (Box 24)
    - Encyclopedia of Modern Health (Box 24)
    - Family Legal Advisor (Box 24)
    - How to Be a Wonderful Hostess (Box 24)
    - Complete Book of Sewing (Box 25)
    - Encyclopedia of Gardening (Box 26)
    - Encyclopedia of Gardening (Box 27)
    - Family Legal Advisor (Box 28)
    - Practical Handyman's Encyclopedia (Box 29)
    - Practical Handyman's Encyclopedia (Box 30)
  - Big Black Book
    - Newspaper advertisements and clippings, 1950 (Box 30)
  - Creative Binder
    - Art of the World, undated (Box 31)
    - Catholic Digest Book Club, 1961 (Box 31)
    - Cosmopolitan Book Club, 1975 (Box 31)
    - Creative Hands, undated (Box 31)
    - Culinary Society, 1968 (Box 31)
    - Encyclopedia of Animal Life, undated (Box 31)
    - Encyclopedia of Photography, undated (Box 31)
    - Works of Mark Twain, 1967 (Box 31)
    - World & Its People, 1964-1967 (Box 31)
    - Newsprint miscellaneous, 1962-1972 (Box 31)
  - Financial Papers
    - Purchase journal, 1980 (Box 31)